Agnese Bartolucci

Visual Designer and PhD Candidate

agnesebartolucci505@gmail.com (+39) 3478257568 Helsinki, Fl

Portfolio | Linkedin | Behance

I am a freelance visual designer with +3 years of professional experience in information and data visualization, UX/UI, and print design. I excel in managing complex projects from concept to delivery, crafting cohesive visual identities, and devising innovative design solutions that are accessible yet engaging.

Areas of expertise

- → Visual Design
- → Information and Data Visualization
- → UX/UI and Interaction Design
- → Printed and Editorial Design
- → Visual Identity Development
- → Visual Reference Curation
- → Concept Development
- → Cross-Media Communication
- → Qualitative and Design Research
- → Academic Writing
- → Digital Archives
- → Intersectional Feminism

Technical skills

- → Expert: Illustrator, InDesign, Photoshop, Lightroom, Figma, HTML, CSS, Excel/Google Sheets, Keynote/PowerPoint, RAWGraphs, Gephi.
- → **Proficient**: P5.js, Tableau, OpenRefine.
- → Basic knowledge: Pr, Ae, ¡Query, D3.js, QGIS.

Languages

- → Italian: Mothertongue
- → English: Proficient IELTS Academic 7.5 (C1) Date 23/02/2023

Soft skills

- → **Presentation**. Experienced in presenting design projects to both internal and external audiences.
- → Teamwork. Experienced in working with teams and collaborating with diverse professionals.
- → Planning. Capable of delivering projects on time through planning and organisation.
- → Problem-solving. Ability to find innovative solutions to problems with a focus on efficacy.
- → Creativity. Developed concepts from a brief through a multi-step process, including research and error-based trials.

Work experience

AUGUST 2024 - PRESENT

Epicmeets, Espoo (Finland) Freelance UX/UI Designer

Leadingd the **design** of the entire **application interface** for a meetings facilitator platform, ensuring **user-friendly** and **visually engaging** experiences.

- → Conducting research to inform design decisions and improve user experience.
- → Collaborating with developers to implement design solutions that enhance application functionality and user engagement.

JUNE 2024 - PRESENT

INT-ACT, European Research Project, Aalto University, Espoo (Finland) Visual Designer

Supporting the promotion and **communication** of research on intangible cultural heritage through **visual and digital design**.

- → Designing informational and promotional materials, including posters, leaflets, and newsletters.
- → Developing and maintaining the project website to aggregate resources.

JULY 2023 - PRESENT

The Visual Agency, Milano (Italy) Freelance Graphic and Data Visualization Designer

Collaborating with a **data visualization and information design** company to **develop publications** for UN agencies and corporations.

- → Designing reports, from layout to data visualization, autonomously.
- → Selecting and curating media for publications from databases.

JANUARY - APRIL 2021

Accurat, Milano (Italy) Data Visualization Designer

Contributed to the **data visualization** team focused on **reporting and printed material**.

- → Designed weekly dashboards for printed newspapers.
- → Collaborated on data visualization projects, such as data posters and reports.

JUNE - SEPTEMBER 2019

La Biennale di Venezia, Venezia (Italy) Graphic Designer

Contributed to the Publishing and Web Office, handling **communication and advertising** for the cultural institution.

- → Developed written and visual material for social networks.
- → Designed printed materials for the International Venice Film Festival.

Education

SEPTEMBER 2023 - PRESENT

Department of Art and Media, Aalto University Doctoral Student

Pursuing a PhD within the Visual Communication Design Research Group, focusing on a **practice-based research project** aimed at **diversifying perspectives in digital archives** through the lens of intersectional feminism under the supervision of Dr. Masood Masoodian.

SEPTEMBER 2018 - APRIL 2022

M.Sc. in Communication Design, Politecnico di Milano Master's Degree (110 cum laude/110)

Developed a **research-based methodology** and consolidated competencies in communication design, with a focus on game design, cross-media communication, **UX/UI design**, and **information and data visualization design**, from data collection to implementation.

SEPTEMBER 2015 - JULY 2018

Bachelor in Communication Design, Politecnico di Milano Bachelor's Degree (108/110)

Gained expertise in **visual representation and graphic techniques**, creating various editorial and digital products, corporate identities, and websites.